All righty.
So the first thing you're going to do is be sure to download the template for this project from the
course.
And once you've unzipped it, you're now where I'm at now.
And I'm just going to go about renaming this, removing the template part to show that I am now going
to actively work on the project.
So the next step will be to open this in visual studio code so we can see that we have an MP for file
here.
This is a video background file that I've added.
And you can see that I've also added some CSF as well.
The very first thing we're gonna do is we're gonna focus on adding a video background.
So the following explanation would be relevant for any project you want to add a video background to.
If you don't want to add a video background to this project and you want to just add a background image
or a background color, you can just remove this video background, CSX from the template and you can
skip ahead to the next video.
But if you are interested in learning about adding a video background and making it mobile responsive,
I'm going to explain that now.
So there are a lot of options out there for stock video, but the one that I'm going to show you is
PIC's eBay.
This is one that I like to use.
It has a lot of great footage and a lot of free options as well.
So if you scroll down, you're just gonna pick a video that you like.
I'm gonna go with this first one here, this Mountain View.
When you click on it, you can see here we have the option to download the video.
And when we click on that, we can see that we have some different quality sizes here.
So you have four K of ten, eighty and 720.
I usually go with 720 for video backgrounds because I will often put a video overlay over them.
So that will mask any kind of lack of quality.
And we also want our videos to be as small as possible so that our Web site loads quickly.
We can see that this 720 video is still 5.2 megabytes, which is pretty big.
So if we download that video, we can actually compress it a little bit further using the Web site.
You compress dot com.
Again, I'll provide a link for this within the course.
We're going to start by simply selecting our file.
And we're going to upload the file and compress just that simple.
So if you remember, our file size was five megabytes and we can see now that we've reduced the file
size by 70 percent.
So now our file size is only one point five megabytes, which I think is very good.
Awesome.
We have our videophone now.
So for our purposes, I've already added a video file within the course and I've taken it a step further.
And I've edited the file to allow it to play forwards and then backwards so that the infinite loop of
the video looks more seamless.
So that file size for that time video is also one point five megabytes.
So it is very small.
So once we have all that sorted out, we can jump back into our code.
And we're going to add to our each team at the top here.
We're going to comment on a title for our video background.
And we're going to have a video element here.
We're going to use the autocomplete to add the class of.
Video dash background.
We're actually going to use another element for our source within our video.
But we also want to set a few attributes on this as well.
So we want our video to loop and be muted and auto play.
So this is because we want it to be a constant video background.
That's why we want it on a loop.
We wanted to play right away as the page loads and the browser rules state, if you're going to play
a video.
It has to be muted.
So that's why we have our muted attribute there as well inside of this video.
We're going to add in our source element and we're gonna give this as our C attribute of time, that
MP for so you see that pretty populated for us.
And then below that, we're going to add in.
A div with the class of video overlay.
So this is going to be a transparent layer.
That's over top of our video.
As I said, it's going to hide any imperfections.
So let's just save that there.
And we're going to launch the project with our lives server extension.
Okay, so that's looking all right, but I know for a fact that the whole clock is visible in the video,
so we're gonna need to adjust some styling.
So back in our see assess, you can see that I've included some styling already.
And specifically for our video background.
So we have position fixed, meaning that on a site where we're scrolling through, we want the background
to always be in one place and we're going to anchor it to the bottom right corner of the page.
We will need to add a width of one hundred VW so that stance or viewport with that is the entire width
of the displayed window.
And we're gonna add a height property of auto.
So let's save that and check it out.
OK, so that's definitely looking better.
We have the whole video now and the whole clock.
But if we check on our mobile view.
We can see that this doesn't work at all because we have a horizontal video and we have a vertical screen
size here, so we're gonna go back to our CSX and we're going to go to the bottom where I've actually
already created a media query for you.
So this is designed for a large smartphone vertical.
So anything less than a max width of 600 pixels will apply these styles.
Remember that all media queries need to be at the bottom because they need to have the last word on
changing the class properties.
So for our video background, we're going to have a height of one hundred VH.
This time, instead of a height of auto and just explicitly we'll write out one hundred VW, even though
we're not changing that.
Just to make it easier to see what's happening.
OK.
And below that, we still need to do one other thing, and that is for our video itself.
We're going to need to add in an object fit property and we're going to use object fit cover.
So the object fit property allows you to make sure that a picture or a video fits whatever container
it's in without being distorted.
So let's save that and check it out.
OK.
So we can see that we've filled up the screen, which is great, but we can see that our clock now is
kind of off the page.
So we want that clock to be more in the center.
We can fix that using the styling object position alongside our object fit.
And you could enter in a horizontal and vertical value to shift the video position within the frame.
But in our case, we only need to shift it horizontally.
So we're only going to add one value and that value is going to be 70 percent.
So if we save that now and check it out, we can see that we have our clock centered nicely in our mobile
view.
OK.
That is awesome.
The very last thing is going to be to add the overlay that I mentioned previously.
The other reason for adding an overlay is so that it's easier to have this be a background image and
still read everything that is within the foreground.
So if we scroll back up to the top.
We can see that we already have a class again for our video overlay in a similar way.
It is fixed position anchored in the top left corner.
We're going to need to add a height of one hundred v h so V for height.
So the entire height of the window and we're going to do a similar thing.
One hundred viewport with.
And then we're going to need to actually add a background color to actually have it look like something.
We're going to use an RGV a value.
And in this case, I'm going to use white.
But you could use black or any other color.
And for the A. which stands for Alpha, also kind of means opacity.
I'm going to have point three five.
So that means it's 35 percent.
See through.
Let's say that and check it out.
OK.
So that allows everything to kind of fade a little bit more into the background.
And you can see if we were to have text here.
It would be a little easier to read because the yellow is not as bright as it was before.
So feel free to adjust as necessary.
The colors and opacity levels, especially if you're using a different video background on a different
project.
Oftentimes I have a black overlay instead of a white one.
But I thought that the white one works better in this case.
All right.
So in the next video, we'll continue creating the UI for our custom countdown project.
I'll see in that one.
Bye for now.